<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at the consecration of the Honourable Dr. Henry Compton, Lord Bishop of Oxford, in Lambeth-Chappel, on Sunday, December 6, 1674 by William Jane ...</title>
            <author>Jane, William, 1645-1707.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1675</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 75 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A46649</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J455</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R21231</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12566531</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12566531</idno>
            <idno type="VID">63348</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A46649)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 63348)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 319:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at the consecration of the Honourable Dr. Henry Compton, Lord Bishop of Oxford, in Lambeth-Chappel, on Sunday, December 6, 1674 by William Jane ...</title>
                  <author>Jane, William, 1645-1707.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 44 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W. Godbid, and are to be sold by R. Littlebury ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1675.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p. [44].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Compton, Henry, 1632-1713.</term>
               <term>Consecration of bishops --  Church of England --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:63348:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:63348:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached at the CONSECRATION Of the HONOURABLE Dr. <hi>HENRY COMPTON,</hi> Lord Biſhop of OXFORD, IN LAMBETH-CHAPPEL, On <hi>Sunday, December</hi> 6. 1674.</p>
            <p>By WILLIAM JANE B.D. Student of <hi>Chriſt-Church,</hi> and Chaplain to his Lordſhip.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>W. Godbid,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>R. Littlebury,</hi> at the <hi>Kings-Arms</hi> in <hi>Little-Britain,</hi> 1675.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:63348:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:63348:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Reverend Father in God <hi>HENRY,</hi> LORD BISHOP of <hi>OXFORD.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough I am too conſcious of the manifold defects of this poor Diſcourſe, to lay any claim to your Lordſhips acceptance, as the encouragement of its Publication; yet I have had ſuch great experience of your Lordſhips favour, as to conceive ſome hopes, that it may find the ſame ſhelter with its Author under your Lordſhips patronage, and protection, When I firſt received your Lordſhips command, which engaged me upon this duty, I eſteemed it a great Honour, than my own ambition could ever have aſpired to. It was happineſs enough for me to bear any part, how inconſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſoever, in that days Solemnity, which in the judgement of all, who have a real kindneſs
<pb facs="tcp:63348:3"/>for the Church, was ſo ſignal an argument of Gods Care and Providence over it. But ſince by my intire reſignation of this weak perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance (as I was in duty bound) to your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips Judgement, it is no longer at my own diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſal, and that, which I thought too mean to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend your Lordſhips <hi>CONSECRATION,</hi> has been thought fit to live with the remembrance of it: I have this further favour to requeſt for it, that I may be allowed to thruſt it forth into the world under your Lordſhips Name. I ſhall only add my unfeigned deſires to the God of Heaven, that (as he has been pleaſed, in this declining Age, to raiſe up to his People, ſuch an able inſtrument of his Glory, ſo) he would go on to give ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs to your Lordſhips deſigns, anſwerable to the expectation of your Country, and the neceſſities of his Church. Which ſhall ever be the daily Prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute> 
               <signed>Your Lordſhips Moſt humbly devoted Chaplain, <hi>WILLIAM JANE.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:63348:3"/>
            <head>
               <q>
                  <bibl>ACTS 20.28.</bibl> Take heed therefore unto your ſelves, and to all the flock, over the which the Holy Ghoſt hath made you overſeers, to feed the Church of God, which he hath purchaſed with his own blood.</q>
            </head>
            <p>WE read in the 17<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
               <hi>verſ.</hi> of this <hi>chap.</hi> that St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſent from <hi>Miletas</hi> to <hi>Epheſus,</hi> and called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>the Elders or Presbyters of the Church.</hi> In this <hi>verſ.</hi> which contains a conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable part of his Viſitation Sermon, he tells them <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the Holy Ghoſt hath made you Biſhops.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This ſeeming confuſion of Names in this and other places of Scripture, indiſcriminately applied to the Paſtors and Officers of the Church, was the pretence of <hi>Aerius,</hi> though Pride and Ambition were the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:63348:4"/>to inferr a like communion in the dignity of Biſhop, and Presbyter, and a total parity in their Office. And though this is ſurely a very ſlender argument to any conſidering men, to violate the unity of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, and to caſhier that form of Government which ad been received univerſally in the Church, from the Apoſtles days unto their own, upon a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, that Antichriſt begun betimes; yet neither is it ſo ſlight and deſpicable, but that it has exerciſed the greateſt Wits in all Ages (even thoſe, in which it cannot be pretended that Truth was twiſted with deſign) in endeavouring a probable ſolution of it. For, to omit the interpretation of ſome, that, ſuch as were Presbyters, when St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſent for them, he here conſecrates Biſhops, by telling them, that the Holy Ghoſt had made them ſo, (as being a groundleſs and arbitrary conjecture,) if we conſult thoſe Opinions which carry the greateſt vogue and reputation in the World, we ſhall ſcarce find one, in which two have conſented, when we have excluded thoſe from the number, who do not pretend to deliver their own ſenſe, but profeſſedly tranſcribe from others. The immediate queſtion, wherein our Authors are divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, is, Whether Biſhop, and Presbyter were two diſtinct Orders at the time of the writing the Books of the New Teſtament, or in a ſmall ſpace of time after, the one were ſuperadded to the other? Thoſe who defend the latter, are further ſubdivided as far as the ſubject will admit. For we are told on the one hand, that the names of Biſhop and Presbyter were once promiſcuouſly given to the inferiour Order
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:63348:4"/>of the Clergy, which were afterwards uſed with diſtinction, when, for the future preventing of Schiſm, Epiſcopacy was introduced upon it<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, which ſeems to be the Judgment of St. <hi>Hierome.</hi> And with greater probability on the other, that they were indifferent appellations of the higher Order of Church Officers, to whom the name of Biſhop be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came then appropriate, when upon the increaſe of their charge, by the multitude of their Proſelites, inferiour Presbyters were univerſally admitted, in ſome meaſure to eaſe them of the burthen. An opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with infinite accuracy and variety of learning firſt cleared and defended by the Reverend Dr. <hi>Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond.</hi> They who have pitcht upon the defence of the former part of the main Queſtion, That both Orders were Coaeval, and diſtinguiſhed from one another by their Author, at the Primitive inſtitution of them, are yet more divided in their explications. For ſome tell us, which Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> admits for probable, that the world <hi>Presbyter</hi> is the Scripture appellative of the inferiour Order of the Clergy; whereas both were common to the Biſhop, in as much as both Offices deſigned by them, were eminently veſted in him. St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> on the contrary, thinks it no inconvenience at all, that the diſtinction of Offices ſhould remain inviolate, notwithſtanding the confuſion of names: Whereas a third Opinion ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently diſtinguiſhed from the other two, aſſerts, that <hi>Biſhop</hi> and <hi>Presbyter</hi> were common denomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the ſecond Order of Prieſt-hood; thoſe whom we now ſtile Biſhops, being at that time called
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:63348:5"/>Apoſtles: A Comment firſt ſuggeſted by <hi>Theodoret,</hi> and ſince maintained by the Judicious <hi>Hooker</hi> in the days of our Forefathers, and with a little variation by the learned <hi>Thorndike</hi> in our own. I have not produced theſe Opinions to compare them with one another, or to examin the ſeveral claims which each of them pretends to truth, but only conſidering them jointly, to make theſe few remarques upon them all.</p>
            <p>And firſt our Aſſertors of the Presbyterian Hierar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, may do well to conſider whoſe Cauſe it is, which is with ſo great eagerneſs maintained by them: No the Cauſe of God, or of his Church, but of a noted Heretick, infamous upon the records of <hi>Epithanius,</hi> St. <hi>Auſtin, Philaſtrius,</hi> and other Fathers of the Church, for the point in queſtion, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently branded for the ſame by the Church it ſelf, whoſe Judgments thoſe Fathers expressly teſtifie. He who was notorious in his own time, for the great diſturber of the word, is now ſet up by our pretended Diſciplinarians for the great Champion of Truth. Nor do they ſo much help themſelves, by ſaying, that <hi>Arrianiſm</hi> was <hi>Aerius</hi> his Hereſie, (and indeed <hi>Epiphanius</hi> calls him an <hi>Arrian</hi> altogether,) as give us occaſion further to obſerve the ſecret, and myſtical connexion between <hi>Arrius</hi> his Doctrin, and <hi>Aerius</hi> his Diſcipline. I do not aſſert, that St. <hi>Ignatius</hi> was Prophetical, in affording the Church through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his Epiſtles, ſuch ſignal teſtimonies againſt both: Yet ſurely they ought to have been well weighted by thoſe learned men, who have rejected the works of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:63348:5"/>that renowned Father, before they choſe, rather than part with a Creature of their own intereſt and fancy, to quit the advantages of thoſe pregnant authorities againſt the <hi>Socinians,</hi> incomparably clearer than all the Fathers of the Church put together, for the firſt 300 years. It is not my purpoſe to lay the Hereſie of <hi>Arrius</hi> to the charge of <hi>Aerius</hi> his followers, or to inquire into the cauſal influence of the one upon the other. But methinks this one reflection, how much <hi>Socinianiſm,</hi> which is but <hi>Arrianiſm</hi> improved, has thriven and proſpered, under the influence of the Presbytery in our neighbour Nation, and (as 'tis great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be ſuſpected) in our own, might prove a motive ſufficient to our diſſenting Brethren to conſider, that Hereſie and Schiſm go uſually together, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce that Schiſmatical Diſcipline, which we have ſeen by woful experience ſo notoriouſly to ſhelter an Heretical Doctrin.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We may obſerve, that however learned men have diſſented as to the particular periods of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencement of either Order, yet in this they all agree, that a ſuperiority of the one above the other, is of Apoſtolical inſtitution: Which obſervation, if any man think to elude from the authorities of <hi>Ignatius, Irenaeus, Origen,</hi> St. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> or St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> I deſire him only to read the learned <hi>Spalatenſis</hi> his <hi>Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> of their Teſtimonies, to make him for ever aſhamed of obtruding them any more. Nay ſo evident is this in the ancient Records of the Church, that the Reverend Biſhop <hi>Bilſon,</hi> out of <hi>Euſebius, He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſippas, Socrates,</hi> St. <hi>Jerome, Epiphanius,</hi> and others;
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:63348:6"/>has given us as exact a Catalogue of the ſucceſſion of Biſhops from the Apoſtles, in the four Apoſtolical Sees, till the firſt Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> as ever the <hi>Roman</hi> Archives could at any time give of their Conſuls, or our common Chroniclers of our Kings, ſince the Conqueſt. From which conſideration, we have ground for an anſwer to a twofold pretence of the Advocates of Presbytery, the one in taking from us the Teſtimony of <hi>Ignatius,</hi> the other, in urging againſt us the Authority of St. <hi>Jerome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the firſt of theſe, it is Monſieur <hi>Dailles</hi>'s principal argument from the Phraſe, that that bleſſed Martyr always makes a diſtinction in the names of Biſhop and Presbyter, which the Apoſtolical writings do ſo confeſſedly confound with one another: But if this be his higheſt evidence, as 'tis manifeſt from his writings, that it is, it is but a ſmall advantage to his Cauſe, and cannot poſſibly ſupport it ſelf againſt any one of thoſe various Hypotheſes, which we juſt now mentioned for a ſolution of the doubt. For firſt, thoſe who think that the Chriſtian Prieſt-hood was originally preſerved in one Order, and at length by the Apoſtles, diſtinguiſhed into two, though after the writing of their Epiſtles, will rationally preſume that the diſtinction of names took its date from the diſtinction of the things, which <hi>Salmaſius</hi> himſelf has owned againſt <hi>Petavius;</hi> and that the ceaſing to uſe the words promiſcuouſly, can never take off from our Author the credit of an Apoſtolical writer, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the pretended inconformity thereof to the writings of the Apoſtles themſelves. But
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:63348:6"/>ſecondly, if we admit their opinion, who conceive the Orders to be diſtinct even then, when the names were common, yet ſuppoſing, that the Scriptures uſe them promiſcuouſly, there is a viſible reaſon, why <hi>Ignatius</hi> ſhould diſtinguiſh: For though two different things may ſometimes indifferently paſs under the ſame names, when either they are uſed to expreſs ſome notion or character, that holds in common to them both, or the ſubject matter determines the ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification; yet when in the ſame propoſition they are both to be repreſented in their proper and diſtinct Idea, according to all the laws of ſpeaking or writing, they will neceſſarily require diſtinct and proper appellations. For how improper had it been to have expreſt the peculiarities of ſeveral dignities, in the ſame Stile and Character, and to make a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference without a diſtinction? How incongruous to common ſenſe, to ſpecify three diſtinct Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical Orders, under the names of Presbyters, Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters and Deacons? and in inforcing the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection of the one to the other, bid Presbyters be ſubject to Presbyters? So that upon the whole, the great quarrel of our adverſaries againſt <hi>Ignatius</hi> is this, that his language is not like their opinion, irra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional and abſurd.</p>
            <p>As to their ſecond refuge, to wit, the authority of St. <hi>Jerome,</hi> I ſhall not interpoſe dogmatically in a Controverſy, in which the moſt able School-men, and other learned Writers are ſo much divided. It is the confident aſſeveration of <hi>Medina,</hi> that St. <hi>Jerome,</hi> and other of the Fathers, agreed in the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:63348:7"/>Hereſie of <hi>Aerius,</hi> but that the Church prudently tolerated that in the one, which for different reaſons it condemned in the other. But upon this principle he will hardly be able to ſecure himſelf againſt the force of <hi>Bellarmine</hi>'s reply, How the Church then continued the pillar and ground of truth, while She forſted Hereticks in her Boſom? And how we can produce the Catholick Fathers as teſtifiers to the Chriſtian Doctrin, who in any one point of it ſymbolized with Hereticks, deſerted the ſenſe of the Church, and turned aſide to the Flocks of the Companions? And ſurely, though St. <hi>Jerome</hi> might differ from others as a private Divine in ſome Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretations of Scripture; yet he ſo long kept himſelf ſound as a Catholick Chriſtian, while he did not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trude any of them againſt the tradition of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and the unity of the Church. And therefore, though I do not agree in his particular opinion, as holding Church Government ſettled by our Savour himſelf, in a clear and manifeſt ſubordination; yet I do not deſire, among all the Fathers of the Church a more pregnant teſtimony, than St. <hi>Jerome</hi> will afford us for a like imparity of Church Officers by Apoſtolical inſtitution: For 'tis he, who in his Epiſtle to <hi>Evagrius,</hi> expressly calls it an Apoſtolical tradition, and founded in the Old Teſtament, that whatſoever priviledge <hi>Aaron</hi> and his Sons, and the <hi>Levites</hi> enjoyed in the Temple, Biſhops, Prieſts, and Deacons might juſtly challenge in the Church. 'Tis he who informs us, on the 23 of St. <hi>Matthew,</hi> of the Apoſtles practice of ordaining Biſhops and Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:63348:7"/>in the ſeveral Provinces, where they Preach'd the Goſpel. 'Tis he who ſtiles the Governours of the reſpective Churches, the Contemporaries of the Apoſtles, by the name of Biſhops, as <hi>Mark</hi> of <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andria, Linus, Cletus,</hi> and <hi>Clemens</hi> of <hi>Rome, James</hi> of <hi>Hieruſalem, Ignatius</hi> of <hi>Antioch,</hi> and <hi>Policarp</hi> of <hi>Smyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na.</hi> And though his opinion were, that Biſhops were poſtnate to Presbyters, as inſtituted for the prevention of Schiſm, yet I appeal to himſelf for a witneſs, that the remedy bears date from the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe, even from that time when it was ſaid at <hi>Corinth,</hi> (which was ſurely in the Apoſtles days,) <hi>I am of</hi> Paul, <hi>I am of</hi> Apollos, <hi>I am of</hi> Cephas, as appears in his Comment upon <hi>Titus.</hi> Surely therefore St. <hi>Jerome</hi> never dreamt that Epiſcopacy was Antichriſtian, nor ever deſigned to effect that from evidence of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which has been ſince attempted by the power of the Sword. <hi>Ignatius</hi> his advice, for the ſubjection of Presbyters to their Biſhop, ſuited well enough with his Principles, as indeed it did with thoſe of all Chriſtendom beſides, till at laſt mens intereſt led them on as to urge Presbytery from St. <hi>Jerome,</hi> ſo to quote St. <hi>Paul</hi> for Rebellion.</p>
            <p n="3">3. But thirdly, from the conſideration of this great variety of Opinions, to ſalve this confuſion of names, it may perhaps be ſeaſonable to enquire, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there be really found in Scripture ſuch a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of names, as is pretended. I am conſcious, that herein I advance an Hypotheſis againſt many great and juſtly venerable Names: And therefore, I ſhall only humbly propoſe a twofold diſtinction,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:63348:8"/>for the clearing thoſe places of Scripture, which concern the point in queſtion. The firſt is, between the Univerſal Church, and thoſe particular Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, wherein Churches were planted under their reſpective Rulers. In the former reſpect I grant, that the word Presbyter is indifferently applied to the Chief Governours of the Church, and that they are the ſame perſons, who are in one place called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and in another, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Which word, whether it were Tranſlated into the Church from the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Synagogue, or elſe taken from Age, which brings experience, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fits for Government, was in thoſe days rather an appellative of dignity, than a diſtinctive character of an Office. And therefore generally in the <hi>Acts of the Apoſtles,</hi> while <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> and <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> were in a manner of the ſame extent, the word <hi>Presbyter,</hi> which in particular Churches was ſtill a title of Honour, had hear a more ample, and undetermined ſignification.</p>
            <p>But if any of our adverſaries take advantage from this conceſſion, I deſire him only to conſider, that the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> are oftner called by the name of <hi>Deacons,</hi> than the chief Governours of the Church, by the name of <hi>Presbyters.</hi> As <hi>Deacons of God and of Chriſt,</hi> 1 Theſſ. 3.2. <hi>Deacons of the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> 2 Cor. 3.6. <hi>Deacons of the Goſpel,</hi> Epheſ. 3.7. <hi>Deacons of righteouſneſs,</hi> 2 Cor. 11.15. <hi>Deacons of the Church,</hi> Col. 1.25. I confeſs that our Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation in theſe, and other parallel places, always read <hi>Miniſters</hi> in ſtead of <hi>Deacons,</hi> (as is obſerved in
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:63348:8"/>thirty places in the vulgar <hi>Latin</hi> of St. <hi>Jerome,</hi>) yet it is the very ſame word, which is rendred <hi>Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons</hi> in the Epiſtles of <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus.</hi> Which containing Apoſtolical Directions for the manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Particular Churches, (<hi>de ſtatu Eccleſiaſtia compoſitae,</hi> as <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſpeaks) diſtinguiſh Church Orders by their Names, and Titles, as well as their Offices, and Powers. And therefore, thought in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the Univerſal Church, the principal Rulers are ſometimes ſtiled <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to ſignify their Superiority over the Brethren; ſometimes <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to denote their immediate Miniſtration, and atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance upon Chriſt, the great Biſhop of our Souls, and Apoſtle of our profeſſion: Yet nothing will follow from hence, but that in particular Churches, they might be both limited, and reſtrained, the one to the ſecond Order of Prieſts, the other, to the Attendants upon the Biſhops: So that this obſervation gives the ſame ground for <hi>Deacons</hi> to conteſt with <hi>Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> as it does for <hi>Presbyters</hi> with <hi>Biſhops.</hi> And thence, becauſe the Apoſtles, and the Brethren, are indifferently called <hi>Diſciples,</hi> they will, by this way of arguing, ſtrengthen the pretence of the <hi>Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendents;</hi> and (as 'tis worded by a learned Writer) <hi>hold the ſtirrop to the Congregations, to throw themſelves out of the Saddle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſecondly, If this Communion of names be pretended in particular Churches, (as at <hi>Philippi, Epheſus,</hi> and <hi>Creet,)</hi> I ſhall crave leave with <hi>Epipha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius,</hi> to make another diſtinction o particular Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches from one another. For he in his Refutation of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:63348:9"/>
               <hi>Aerius</hi> his Argument drawn from the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of names, objects to him his not underſtanding the Hiſtories of the Primitive plantation of Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, aſſerting, That at the firſt forming of them, (which could not be perfected in an inſtant) there were in ſome places, Biſhops without Presbyters, and in other, Presbyters without Biſhops; which could be no inconvenience for a ſmall ſpace of time, ſince thoſe, who planted them, were ſufficiently ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled to ſupply the defect of either. He never ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved this confuſion of names, which has been ſince pretended, (as neither did any, that went before him) but thought this one conſideration to be valid enough, to convince his adverſary both of errour in Interpreting Scripture, and of Ignorance in the Monuments of the Church.</p>
            <p>But granting all that we have hitherto aſſerted, and moreover, that the objection from the plurallity of Biſhops, mentioned at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> and <hi>Philippi,</hi> be fully taken off upon this preſumption, that in the Apoſtles days, there were more Biſhops than one in a City, 'till a more perfeſt Coaleſcence was at length made between the <hi>Jewiſh,</hi> and the <hi>Gentile</hi> Converts; yet notwithſtanding, it may be ſtill de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, What is all this to the caſe before us? For here in a particular Church (the Church of <hi>Epheſus)</hi> the ſame perſons in the ſame Speech, are called both <hi>Presbyters</hi> and <hi>Biſhops.</hi> To which I anſwer, that if <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> denote the <hi>univerſal Church,</hi> my firſt diſtinction holds good: But if not, I have the Teſtimony of <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> (an authority
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:63348:9"/>next to Apoſtolical,) to extend the word <hi>Church,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the City of <hi>Epheſus;</hi> and <hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Presbyters,</hi> beyond one Order of the Clergy. For ſo he writes in his Third Book, and Fourteenth Chapter; <hi>In Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leto enim Convocatis Epiſcopis, &amp; presbyteris, qui erant ab Epheſo &amp; a reliquis proximis Civitatibus.</hi> To which the late Vindicator of Monſieur <hi>Daillee,</hi> ſeems to return an anſwer, by giving <hi>Irenaeus</hi> the lye; <hi>A Divi Lucae narratione ſeorsim abit.</hi> But ſurely, when St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſays, <hi>verſ.</hi> 25 <hi>All you, among whom I have gone Preaching the Kingdom of God,</hi> he ſeems to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate a greater extent than the ſingle City of <hi>Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> will amount to, and conſequently, to give us ſome ground for a reconcilement between <hi>Irenaeus</hi> and St. <hi>Luke:</hi> And therefore, I ſhall make no other uſe of our Authors reply, than to obſerve another inſtance of the hard fate of the Fathers of the Church, however ancient and Apoſtolical, when they croſs mens Intereſts and Opinions. For if we urge them with <hi>Ignatius,</hi> he is ſpurious, and ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitious, and therefore to be rejected; if with <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> he is falſe and fabulous, and ſo not to be believed.</p>
            <p>I have thus far explained the difficulty ariſing from the phraſe of the Text, and therein juſtified my diſſent from our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tranſlation, in reading <hi>Biſhops</hi> inſtead of <hi>Overſeers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as the Reverend Fathers of our Church, at His Majeſties Reſtauration, thought fit to change the place, which this paſſage of Scripture formerly had in the Book of <hi>Ordination;</hi> ſo I have here given ſome reaſon, why that which was formerly a part
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:63348:10"/>of the <hi>Epiſtle</hi> for the <hi>Ordination</hi> of <hi>Prieſts,</hi> may now be made the <hi>Text</hi> of a Sermon, at the <hi>Conſecration</hi> of a <hi>Biſhop.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which are compriſed all the principal argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which may enforce a Biſhops vigilance and circumſpection, in the management of his Paſtoral Charge, and urge home the Caution of the Text, <hi>Take heed therefore.</hi> The Topicks to perſwade a more than ordinary Care in any duty, are generally four: All which we meet with in this place.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The excellency of the thing Cared for, the Church of God, <hi>which he hath purchaſed with his own blood.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. The Perſon Concernment in it, ariſing from the peculiar truſt repoſed in him, <hi>the Holy Ghoſt hath made you Biſhops.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. The danger of miſcarriage, in the following words, <hi>For after my departure ſhall grievous wolves enter in among you.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4. The poſſibility of preſerving the thing Cared for; which though not fully expreſt, is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently implied in theſe Phraſes, of <hi>Taking heed to your ſelves of feeding the Church.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Of theſe briefly, and in the their order, as far as the greater buſineſs of the day will permit.</p>
            <p>And firſt, of the excellency of the thing Cared for, <hi>The Church of God, which he hath purchaſed with his own blood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where we may obſerve a manifeſt point of <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Doctrin, by immediate conſequence dedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible from the words (to wit) the Divinity of our
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:63348:10"/>Savour: A truth, which offers it ſelf to us, with ſuch uncontrollable clearneſs, that the <hi>Socinian</hi> fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it ſtaring him directly in the face, to elude the evidence, corrupts the Text, reads <hi>Chriſti</hi> in ſtead of <hi>Dei,</hi> (which yet in the <hi>Syriack</hi> Edition, whence he takes it, ſeems rather an Expoſition than a Verſion) and thereby offers the ſame violence to the Temporal Word of God, as he had done before to the Eternal. And as ſome Barbarous Nations are ſaid to have cut out the Tongues of their abuſed Captives, leſt they ſhould diſgrace them, by publiſhing their wrongs and injuries, having firſt robb'd Chriſt of his Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, he finds himſelf obliged to rob the Church of the Scriptures, which bear witneſs to the truth of it.</p>
            <p>But this is conſiſtent enough with his Principles: For having ſo looſly ſettled the notion of a Church, as to make an univerſal Apoſtacy commence from the very death of the Apoſtles, he had no great reaſon to over-value the Blood of Chriſt, which had procured ſuch a ſhort lived, and uncertain bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit. He might juſtly preſume the price was not very great, where the purchaſe was ſo little regarded. But let <hi>Socinus</hi> go on with as much ſcorn, as he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, to ſlight the one, and trample upon the other; a true Catholick Biſhop, that knows it coſt more to redeem a Soul, will hence take an argument to infer, that his watchfulneſs over his Flock, ought to riſe in ſome proportion to that eſteem and value, which his Lord and Maſter hath ſet upon it. He will not forfeit, or betray his truſt, for the ſake of ſilver and gold, and thoſe other corruptible things,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:63348:11"/>which he well knows, were utterly unable to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem it: But conſidering it as purchaſed by the blood of Chriſt, he will judge it worthy to be preſerved and cared for, though with the expence or hazard of his own: It was for the Churches ſake, that the Son of God came down from Heaven, emptyed himſelf of his Glory, exhauſted a richer than all the world could afford beſides. For this end, was the great Biſhop of our Souls <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (according to the critical im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance of the word, Conſecrated to his Epiſcopal Office) by <hi>ſtrong crying and tears,</hi> by death and blood. So coſtly and chargeable was his Conſecration, that he ſeems to decline, and deprecate it, with a <hi>Nolo Epiſcopari, Father if it be poſſible, let this Cup paſs from me;</hi> And we may juſtly thinks his Father would have ſaved him, if a meaner ranſom could have ſaved the World.</p>
            <p>This then (Holy Fathers) is that Sacred <hi>depoſitum</hi> which is committed to your Charge, ſo often repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the Office of the Church for this Solemnity, even the greateſt gift that ever was poured forth upon the Sons of Men, the precious blood of the Son of God, the unſearchable riches of Chriſt. It lies upon you therefore to teſtify, that the blood of Chriſt was not ſpilt in vain, and to accompliſh that redemption, which your Lord hath merited: That neither through your miſcarriage, may Chriſt be defeated of his purchaſe, which are the Souls of men; nor the Church of her price, and priviledge, the merit of her Saviours Blood.</p>
            <p>But I paſs from the invaluable excellency of the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:63348:11"/>thing cared for, to the ſecond motive of the Text, even your own concernment in it, ariſing from the consideration of the Perſon by whom you are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted, <hi>The Holy Ghoſt hath made you Biſhops.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As the gift of the Holy Ghoſt was the ſignal pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative, whereby the Church of Chriſt outvyed the luster of the Temple, and which our Saviour at his departure, thought and abundant compenſation to his Diſciples for the defect of his Corporal pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence with them; ſo amongſt all the noble purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, for which he was then poured forth upon all Fleſh, there is no one thing repreſented in Scripture, which he ſeems to have a more viſible, and imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate concern in, than the erecting and authorizing a Miniſtry, commiſſioning for Church Offices, and enabling for the diſcharge.</p>
            <p>This is that great Work, which, however meanly eſteemed, or ſcornfully treated in this World, was in the eſtimation of our Saviour, one of the choiceſt Largeſſes, which at his Triumphant aſcending far above all Heavens, he thought fit to ſhed forth upon his Church. And thence we find, <hi>Matthew</hi> 28.28. that when after his aſcenſion, he tells his Diſciples, <hi>all power is given to me in Heaven and in Earth;</hi> the firſt and great inſtance, wherein he imparts it to his Followers, is a Commiſſion for the Miniſtry, <hi>Go ye therefore, and teach all nations:</hi> And accordingly, that triumphant <hi>Pſalm,</hi> which the ſweet Singer of of <hi>Iſrael</hi> prepared to be Sung at the removal of the Ark, whence God did uſe to deliver his Oracles from between the Cherubins, the adumbration of our
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:63348:12"/>Saviours removal from Earth to Heaven, is by the Apoſtle repeated and accommodated thereto, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.8. and completion verified in this, <hi>that he gave ſome Apoſtles, ſome Prophets, ſome Evangeliſts, ſome Paſtors and Teachers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe were the Gifts he then received for men, as a ſtanding Teſtimony, that, though himſelf were departed, the Lord God dwelt ſtill among them. No wonder therefore to find in the Text, <hi>the Holy Ghoſt hath made you Biſhops;</hi> ſince their very employment, is one of his peculiar donatives, as that of <hi>Timothy</hi> is expressly called his <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in each of his Epiſtles.</p>
            <p>It were an eaſie matter to extend this conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion beyond the Church of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> and to trace the intereſt of the Holy Ghoſt, in conſtituting Church Governors from the firſt Foundation of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity to this day, to find him not only once fitting <hi>Bezaleel,</hi> and <hi>Aholiab</hi> with Skill, and Wiſdom, for the Building a material Tabernacle; But in every Age, empowering and qualifying ſerviceable Perſons, for the Strength and Beauty of his Church. This was the Commiſſion, which the great Biſhop of our Souls produced for himſelf, at his entrance upon his Paſtoral Charge, <hi>The Spirit of the Lord is upon me, and hath anointed me to Preach the Goſpel, Luke</hi> 4.18. Nor was this merely perſonal to our Saviour, as <hi>Baronius</hi> would have it, who confines that Text to the firſt year of our Saviours Preaching; but when he comes to Ordain a Succeſſion, we ſhall find this to be the Rite, and Solemnity of the Conſecration: <hi>As my Father ſent me, ſo ſend I you.</hi> Where, if the ſimilitude
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:63348:12"/>will not infer the Gift of the Holy Ghoſt, the next words will expreſs it, <hi>And he breathed on them,</hi> and ſaid, <hi>receive ye the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> John 20.21. And after that he bids them tarry at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> till they were <hi>endued with power from above,</hi> Luke. 24.49. which is Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted <hi>Acts</hi> I. <hi>endued with the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> The Holy Ghoſt muſt firſt ſay <hi>ſeparate,</hi> before <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> undertake the Charge. <hi>Acts</hi> 13.2. Nor could the laying on of hands have made <hi>Timothy</hi> a Biſhop, unleſs Prophecy had gone before: And leſt theſe ſhould ſeem choice, and peculiar inſtances of an extraordinary deputation of ſome perſons, to whom God was pleaſed to vouchſafe extraordinary Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations of himſelf, (and we know thoſe, who have hence inferred, that <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> were Evangeliſts) not fixed and ſtanding Officers of the Church, (as <hi>Walo Meſſalinus,</hi> and others.) We have the full atteſtation of <hi>Clemens Romanus,</hi> in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> of the Apoſtles practice of Ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Biſhops, out of thoſe whom they had Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, after they had firſt tryed, and approved them by the Revelation of the Holy Ghoſt, whom <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus</hi> alſo calls <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ſuch as the Holy Spirit had deſigned, and ſignified to them:</hi> Nay, ſo clear is this truth of the Spirits, ſuperintendency in theſe great Solemnities, through the ancient Monuments of the Church, that Cardinal <hi>Baronius,</hi> however a ſtiff Aſſerter of the <hi>Popes</hi> Incroachments, both upon the right of Biſhops, and the Holy Ghoſts prerogative in their delegation; yet is forced by
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:63348:13"/>the evidence of truth, to confeſs, that as Chriſt breathed the Holy Ghoſt upon the Apoſtles, in like manner have they transferred the ſame upon all their Succeſſors to this day, in as much, as they muſt undoubtedly partake of the Spirit of Chriſt, who miniſter in Chriſts ſtead, in the Sacred Offices of his Church.</p>
            <p>It is an opinion, faſtned upon <hi>Durandus,</hi> that when God made the World, he threw it out of his Hands, and left all things in it ever ſince to act of themſelves, from thoſe ſeveral principles of Life and Motion, which he diſtributed among them at the Creation. A like conceit have ſome endeavoured to introduce into the Church, that the world <hi>Spirit,</hi> in Holy Scripture, is to be confined to that plentiful effuſion of it upon the Apoſtles, on the day of <hi>Pente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſt,</hi> thoſe miraculous Gifts and Graces, which in the infancy of Chriſtianity, accompanied the Preaching of the Goſpel. Which Commiſſion being perſonal to the Apoſtles, by conſequence, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pired withy them; ſo that their Succeſſors in the work of the Miniſtry, for any concern the Holy Ghoſt has in them, are left to ſhift for themſelves, or at moſt, to ſubſiſt upon that ſtock of reputation, which was at firſt gained in the World, by the mighty Signs and Wonders of their inſpired, and gifted Predeceſſors. But as the Schools, from the common Principles of Reaſon, have ſolidly main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained againſt the former, that ſo precarious and dependent is the Creature, as ſuch, both in its being, and operation, that ſhould God ſubtract his influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:63348:13"/>and concurſe, whereby every moment he makes it, and works with it all its operations, are immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately ſuſpended, the whole Creation falls aſunder, and molders into its primitive Confuſion; ſo a like aſſertion, if the Scripture were ſilent, would common ſenſe and experience ſuggeſt to us, for a Confutation of the latter. For ſo powerful are the batteries that are daily made by the Luſts of Men, and the Malice of the Devil, and ſo impotent and unarmed a thing is the Church of God, conſidered in it ſelf, to withſtand the aſſaults of either, that not only the gates of Hell, but the powers of the World, would long ago have finally prevailed againſt it; but that it was ever Founded upon the Rock of Ages, and Supported by the Hand of Heaven.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The daily Sacrifice had long ſince ceaſed, and the abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of deſolation been ſtanding in the Holy Place.</hi> And Chriſts Myſtical Body had not ſo long ſurvived his Natural, did not the ſame Spirit, which was at firſt breathed into it, go on continually to actuate, and enliven it. Surely therefore, now, as well as then, <hi>there is a heavenly Treaſure in earthen Veſſels,</hi> and the continuance of <hi>the Miniſtration is from God, and not from us.</hi> He is God, and not Man, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>the Sons of</hi> Jacob <hi>are not conſumed.</hi> Biſhops are the Stars in Chriſt's own right Hand, and from this ariſes the utter impoſſibility for the Tayl of the Dragon, to ſweep them away, for the force of Men to pluck them thence, or for the powers of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to extinguiſh them. The Apoſtles then, did not carry their Commiſſions with them to the other
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:63348:14"/>World, which, they knew, were left them for a perpetuity of ſucceſſion in this, both for them, and their Heirs for ever. 'Twas he told his Diſciples, who was never yet taxed with being worſe than his word, <hi>Behold I am with you to the end of the World,</hi> He could not mean it, doubtleſs, of their perſons, who did not long ſurvive him, nor can the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, notwithſtanding ſome bold Criticiſms upon the words, refer to any other period of time, than that, wherein the Fabrick of the World ſhall be diſſolved, when Time it ſelf ſhall be no more. He is ſtill therefore with their Succeſſors, as he was with them after his Aſcenſion, <hi>Vicariâ ſpiritûs preſentiâ,</hi> as <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſpeaks, though not in the various di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributions, and admirable virtue of their <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the extent of their Juriſdiction, and extraordinary meaſure of their revelations; yet in the effectual Adminiſtration of all thoſe Ordinances, which were to reſide for ever in his Church, in order to the ſalvation of the World. Such are <hi>the Preaching of the Word, Adminiſtration of the Sacraments, Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daining Miniſters, Ordering Church-diſcipline, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicting Cenſures, and the power of the Keys:</hi> All which, as long as they are neceſſary, for the edify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Body of Chriſt, ſo long is the preſence of the Holy Ghoſt neceſſary, to authorize perſons to diſpence them. Well therefore may we preſume, that our <hi>Veni Creator Spiritus,</hi> is not ſaid in vain at this great Solemnity, nor can we poſſibly over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>look that viſible inſtance of his peculiar Preſence, in the Conſecration of this day.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:63348:14"/>
            <p>For though we live in an Age, wherein not only the work of the Miniſtry is become the deriſion of Fools, but even wiſe Men pretend to diſcern the dreadful ſymptoms of a departing Candleſtick, and a tottering Church; yet it hath pleaſed him, who perfecteth ſtrength in weakneſs, and is neareſt at hand in the greateſt exigents, to raiſe up the Sons of Nobles, to become the Princes of his People, to ſtop the Mouths of the one, and to refute the Prog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſticks of the other.</p>
            <p>He places over us, in the ſame perſons, both <hi>a glory,</hi> and <hi>a defence;</hi> by the one, to take off ſcandal, by the other, to ſtrengthen the Church. Bleſſed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be the Name of our great God, in whoſe Hand are the Hearts of Kings that hath ſtirred up the heart of Ours, to make this cloſer connexion between the Civil and Eccleſiaſtical intereſts, and in the ſame choice, effectually to provide for the perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuity of the Church, and for the eſtabliſhment of his Throne.</p>
            <p>We have thus ſeen, that God has not failed hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to to make good his promiſe to his Church, that the <hi>Comforter ſhall abide with it for ever:</hi> But ſince theſe inſtances have not proved ſo ſucceſsful, as to ſilence the Contradiction of fooliſh and unreaſonable men, I ſhall briefly conſider ſome of the moſt plauſible pretences that are made uſe of, to ſhake the ſtability of the Church, and turn the Holy Ghoſt out of his Office.</p>
            <p>Firſt then, <hi>the Holy Ghoſt hath made you Biſhops,</hi> and therefore not the Civil Magiſtrate. It is an
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:63348:15"/>objection of the <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> againſt the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, that the power of Order hath ceaſed in our Church, ever ſince the departure from the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> as being now utterly diſſolved into the Kings deputation of Commiſſioners for the Adminiſtration of Eccleſiaſtical Affairs. And though the ſcandal be abundantly refuted, by the ſacred Rites, and Solemnities of this day; yet we have had thoſe among our ſelves, who in ſtead of denying the charge, as they juſtly might, have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to juſtifie the Church, by owning the accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation. For we are told, by the Diſputers of this World, that the Church is nothing elſe, but a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Common-wealth, and that all pretence of Divine authority and obligation upon Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, abſtracted from the power of the Sword, is a meer Impoſture, and deſtructive to the State. Thus, by the old Stratagem of the Enemy of Man-kind, is the Church, as was once its Author, traduced as an enemy to <hi>Caeſar:</hi> Though, I hope, the Caſe may be ſo plainly ſtated between both, as to vindicate the Rights of the one, without incurring the Jealouſie of the other.</p>
            <p>The contrary aſſertion, to what we have laid down, can be maintained only upon one of theſe three Grounds.</p>
            <p>Firſt, that there was no right for Chriſtians to aſſociate together for the Worſhip of God, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the profeſſion of Chriſtianity, antecedent to the Command or Allowance of the Civil power.</p>
            <p>Or Secondly, ſuppoſing a Society of <hi>Chriſtians,</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:63348:15"/>that there was no right of Rule or Government, veſted in the Officers and Paſtors of it.</p>
            <p>Or thirdly, ſuppoſing a Church power, that it eſcheated to the ſupream Magiſtrate, when the Church became incorporate into the Civil ſtate.</p>
            <p>The firſt of theſe, though perhaps the ultimate reſolution of the other two, reſolves it ſelf into Blaſphemies beyond the confutation of the Pulpit. We muſt thence pronounce all the Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Chriſtians, even thoſe aſſemblings of themſelves together, which the Apoſtle commands his <hi>Hebrews,</hi> not to forſake, to be ſo many unlawful Conventicles, and not exempt the firſt Council at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> from the accuſation which we are ſure was managed by the preſiding of the Holy Ghoſt. We muſt affix the blackeſt note of Infamy upon the Apoſtles and the Primitive <hi>Chriſtianſ,</hi> and aſcribe a right to the <hi>Heathen</hi> Magiſtrates, which ſhall juſtify the perſecution of <hi>Chriſtianity.</hi> We muſt arraign the Noble Army of Martyrs, whoſe He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roical Courage we hitherto ſolemnize of foul ſelf-Murther, as well as folly, in being prodigal of their Blood, to no purpoſe, running upon the Sword without a warrant, and laying down their lives in the defence of a propoſition, when they had no obligation to profeſſ it, and ſo execute their Names, and Memories, as the <hi>Heathen</hi> did their perſons, by owning, that they ſuffered deſervedly. But ſurely, if we have not forfeited our Faith, as well as our Charity, we may conclude they had hard meaſure enough at their Perſecutors tribunals, and therefore may be diſmiſt from ours.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:63348:16"/>
            <p>The ſecond pretence is ſomewhat more plauſible, That there is ſuch a Society, as a Church, and Officers placed in it, but ſuch, whoſe only buſineſſ it is to teach and to declare the will of God, without any rule or authority committed to them, over thoſe who ſhal1 receive it. Againſt which we might reaſon with the Learned <hi>Grotius,</hi> upon <hi>Luke</hi> 6.22. that there is no neceſſity of aſſigning a poſitive and expreſſ Precept in Holy Scripture for granting the Society of the Church, eſtabliſhed by God; all thoſe things are virtually commanded in it, which are abſolutely neceſſary to preſerve it in its purity, and its being. Such is the power of Diſcipline and Government, as is evident, from the common notion of Societies in general, and the peculiar nature of this. But not contenting our ſelves toargue merely from natural Reaſon, in a poſitive Inſtitution of this kind, as tranſcends the ſublimeſt diſquiſitions, and cloſeſt deductions of it, if we conſult the pattern in the Mount, or the ſettlement of the Church in the New Teſtament, which contains the Covenant of Grace, whereupon it is founded, we ſhall find in the Church, as in the Ark, which was the Type of it, <hi>the rod of Aaron,</hi> as well as <hi>the Tables of the Law,</hi> and diſcover in it the manifeſt traces of a paternal and imperative, though no coercive Jurisdiction. We ſhall there find the Enacting of Laws, as in the firſt Council at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> a promulgation of the Decrees that were made by the Apoſtle and Elders, which was done by <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas,</hi> through the Cities, <hi>Acts</hi> 16.4. a Judiciary pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſ
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:63348:16"/>againſt offenders, I. <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.19. a puniſhment of the guilty, as appears in the inceſtuouſ <hi>Corinthian,</hi> and in the ſame inſtance, the abſolution of the Peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, and relaxation of the Cenſure. We ſhall find there the perſons with whom the management of theſe great affairs was intruſted, dignified and diſtinguiſhed by the Titles of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; all which import Rule and Authority, whereto they were ſolemnly Sanctified and ſet apart, by a viſible and Sacred Rite of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of hands: All which, if they are duly, and impartially conſidered, will ſufficiently evidence, that theſe things were ſomething more than Page<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antry and Show, that there was a Government in the World, ſubſiſting upon a different claim, from that of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, that Chriſt ſent forth his Apoſtles, not only as Sheep among Wolves, but as Paſtors among Sheep; and that he had a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, though not of this World.</p>
            <p>Thirdly therefore, that this Spiritual Authority was diſſolved, and melted down into the Civil, when the World came into the Church, and the Empire became Chriſtian, muſt be made out one of theſe three wayes; either from <hi>the original right of the Empire, the revelation of God,</hi> or <hi>the reaſon of the thing.</hi> The right of the Empire ſtands upon this <hi>baſis,</hi> that the Power of the Church depended upon the confederation and conſent of Chriſtians, which the Supream Magiſtrate may at his pleaſure draw back and reſume into himſelf.</p>
            <p>But firſt, againſt this pretended agreement of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:63348:17"/>the Primitive <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> we may argue, from all thoſe inſtances of the agency of the Holy Ghoſt; in conſtituting Church Officers, which we have mentioned already: All which bear evident Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony to a poſitive Inſtitution, and a Divine Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</p>
            <p>But ſecondly, ſuppoſing it for the preſent, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, Whether the Primitive <hi>Chriſtians</hi> had a right to enter into thoſe confederacies antecedent to the command or allowance of the Empire, or no? If not, we are brought back again to the Apoſtate Principles of the <hi>Leviathan.</hi> And though I ſhould grant Mr. <hi>Selden,</hi> that <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> after the death of our Lord, had the allowance of the State, by that Act of the Empire, which tolerated the <hi>Jews;</hi> Yet to ſay, that the Society was legally diſſolved, when they came more narrowly to be enquired into, is to take off the Glory of Martyrdom from thoſe, who notwithſtanding the Edicts of the Empire, kept on the Aſſemblies of the Church, and the brand of Apoſtacy from others, who pleaded for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, that they had left them. If it be ſaid, that the Society of the Church, had this right of mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Confederation, the caſe is juſt where it was. For whether the Governours of the Church ſubſiſt immediately by Divine Right, or no; yet if the Church, as a Society, for the better maintaining of Chriſtianity by Divine Right, be enabled to appoint them, obedience is juſtly due to them in the Affairs of Chriſtianity, independent upon the Powers of this World. And ſurely, water will riſe
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:63348:17"/>no higher than the place from whence it deſcended; nor can the Empire ever come to challenge the Rights of the Church, which were antecedent to any Act of it, unleſs it have pleaſed the Great Soveraign of both, to declare his Pleaſure for transferring them. For if the Church be a Society, immediately conſtituted by God, then can it not be diſſolved in time, but by the ſame Power, which eſtabliſhed it at the beginning. But where is there to be found in Scripture, any ſhadow of an Ordinance for this Temporary condition of the Church? Surely all things there ſeem to run in another ſtrain. If <hi>Timothy</hi> be inſtructed by St. <hi>Pauls;</hi> how to behave himſelf in the Church of God, he is forthwith charged to keep the Commandment unblameable, untill the appearing of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt. If the Angel of <hi>Thyatira</hi> be repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended for the remiſs exerciſe of his Authority, he has likewiſe a command from our Saviour, to hold it faſt and maintain it 'till his coming. Chriſt did not appoint Paſtors in his Church, only 'till the time of <hi>Conſtantine;</hi> but 'till we all come in the unity of Faith, and the Knowledge of the Son of God, to a perfect man. Which woful experience will aſſure us was not effected in <hi>Conſtantine</hi>'s dayes, nor will it ever be, 'till the conſummation of all things: The darkneſs which over-ſpreads our underſtandings, can never be diſpelled, but by the Light of Glory; nor can our hearts be entirely reunited, but by that Charity, which never fails.</p>
            <p>There remains therefore only the laſt way of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:63348:18"/>arguing, and that is from the reaſon of the thing: For thus it is pleaded, that unleſs both Powers re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide intirely in the ſame Perſons, they muſt both expect the ſame Fate which attends a Kingdom di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided againſt it ſelf, by reaſon of daily and vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious contentions between the Church and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, the Sword of Juſtice and the Shield of Faith; and which is more than this, in the breaſt of every Chriſtian, between the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> and the <hi>Man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus what we deny to Nature, ſhall be effected by Grace; the Goſpel of Peace ſhall retrieve a State of War; and this pretended Order and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, become but another name for Confuſion.</p>
            <p>And though I have before barred this Method of Reaſoning, by ſuppoſing Chriſtianity to be a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive Conſtitution of Divine Grace, (albeit Religion in general, be a moral Virtue,) yet becauſe the Charge is of ſo high a Nature, as if the Churches claim of Power from God, rendred it uncapable of the Protection of his Vice-gerent, and Chriſts coming to fit Inhabitants for another World, were a means to diſ-people this; I am obliged, for the removal of ſuſpition, to propoſe theſe following conſiderations.</p>
            <p>Firſt therefore, though other Religions may be juſtly preſumed prejudicial to the publick Peace, in as much as the Devil, who is the Inventor of them, is withal the Author of Confuſion in the Government of the World; yet ſuch is the peculiar <hi>genius</hi> of Chriſtianity, that where-event is, either Preached or Received, it can create no Jealouſie in
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:63348:18"/>in the State. The ground upon which this Aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſtands, is this, that it diſclaims all title to the Sword, but leave him that takes it, to periſh with it, though it be drawn in the defence of Chriſt himſelf.</p>
            <p>Surely he that had <hi>legions of Angels</hi> at his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, in ſtead of ſending forth Apoſtles to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert men to the Faith, might have Commiſſioned Generals, to deſtroy the Unbelievers. But this, in the eſteem of Infinite Wiſdom, was judged more Military than Religious, and the way of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagating his Goſpel had been inconſiſtent with the deſign of it.</p>
            <p>This therefore being ſuppoſed, that Chriſtianity leaves the power of the Sword in thoſe hands, in which it finds it, how can it poſſibly make any alteration, as to any Temporal Condition, vhich is profeſſedly maintained by it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And therefore, that great bugbear of <hi>Imperium in Imperio</hi> need not be ſo terrible as men would make it, as long as their Objects, Ends, and Offices , ſtand as really di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed as their Obligations. And theſe were the Thoughts that Chriſtians had of their Religion, as long as Chriſtianity was underſtood. In the Church then, as of old in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> there was no Smith to provide Swords and Spears, though againſt their perſecuting <hi>Philiſtins.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And though this intire renunciation of all claim to any thing wherein the Civil Power was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned, proved unable to protect them, either from Slander or Perſecution; yet that which exited the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:63348:19"/>rage and fury of their Enemies, was rather an averſeneſs to the Chriſtians Doctrine, than any jealous concern for their own ſafety. It being abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly evinced by the ancient Apologies of the Church Writers againſt the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> that though they did not believe the <hi>Chriſtian Faith,</hi> they could not in Civil juſtice perſecute a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> No, their Lives <hi>then</hi> were a Tranſcript of their Doctrin, and their Obedience was look'd upon as a tryal of their <hi>Faith.</hi> To obey Authority, was taught and practiſed under a <hi>Nero,</hi> and their Submiſſions were as unparalelled as their Provocations. And we may truly ſuppoſe under the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperours, that had the Doctrine of Obedience been as throughly recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by their <hi>Heathen</hi> Subjects, as it was Preached by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> and practiſed by his believing <hi>Romans,</hi> they had effectually provided for the publick tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quility without any farther need of Forts and Armies to ſecure it.</p>
            <p>But ſecondly, the ſuppoſal of Divine Right in the Governours of the Church, where Chriſtianity is received into the State, abates nothing of the natural Right of the Civil Power, in matters of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. This aſſertion depends upon the foregoing: For if Chriſtianity makes no change at all in any Temporal concern of the World, then a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> State has the ſame right of ordering the Affairs of Chriſtianity, ſo that nothing be done by virtue of it, which may create a prejudice to the State, as any other Kingdoms of the World have in that Religion which they profeſs. For no Nation ever
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:63348:19"/>yet openly pretended that great holdneſs with their Gods, as to make Religion, at pleaſure, become either true or falſe; but they therefore profeſs any Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, becauſe they firſt ſuppoſe it to be true. Religion therefore being firſt eſtabliſh'd, whatſoever it be, all that afterwards follows, is a nomination of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to diſpence it, giving Laws for the due Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration o it; ſetting bounds and limits to the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe, calling Aſſemblies to conſult about it, ratifying their Decrees with civil Sanctions, and receiving Appeals, in caſe of a corrupt Management, and an unjuſt Sentence. All which, Chriſtianity ſo entirely devolves upon the Magiſtrate, that thoſe who have taken the greateſt pains to clear the fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental Right of the Church, have withal pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the moſt able, and vigorous Aſſertors of thoſe inherent Prerogatives of the Crown: And, when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they come to be diſowned through the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> World, then, and not before, let the Church lye for ever under that guilt and <hi>odium,</hi> which men now make it their buſineſs to caſt upon it. Let Kings ceaſe to be <hi>her nurſing Fathers,</hi> and Queens <hi>her nurſing Mothers:</hi> In the mean time it bears the ſame notion with Religion in general, in reference to the powers of the World, ſave only in this, that it addreſſes it ſelf to them with greater obligations to take it into their protection, that is, with greater evidence of a Divine Authority.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, however it has come to paſs, through the Debaucheries of Men, and the Malice of the Devil, that Religion (as a Learned man obſerves)
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:63348:20"/>has been a politick Engin in ſome mens hands, and made uſe of for the battery, as by others, for the defence of the State; yet the Government of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which is the ſubject of our preſent debate, ſtands as clear, and juſtifiable to the World altogether as our common Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p>For as for the Eſſentials of it, if once Religion be diſmiſt from the Accuſation of turning the World upſide down, I would fain know, what further latent miſchief can be in this, that one man in a certain Precinct, or Dioceſs, take care, that all, who profeſs Religion, live in obedience and conformity to the Rules of it. And this is all which we claim, as eſſentially pertaining to Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Juriſdiction. As for the Secular advantages of Temporal Priviledges, and Power, ſince we thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully own them to be the meer acceſſions of Humane bounty, they can cauſe no jealouſie in the Author of them, 'till we ſee the Streams contend with the Fountain, and the Beams of the Sun, with the Sun it ſelf. Our Church never owned their Religion, who compare the Church to the Sun, and the Empire to the Moon, but Receives all theſe Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall favours, as the Arbitrary donatives of the Civil Power, not in any wiſe her own, but entirely a borrowed luſtre. And, which is for the Eternal reputation of our Church, ſhe has learn'd to want them, as well as to abound with them; and can be equally loyal both in the loſs, and the enjoyment. Which we need go no further for a proof of, then her Canons, and her Practice: Both which, have
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:63348:20"/>given us an evident demonſtration, that ſhe was the ſureſt ſupport, during the ſtanding of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Monarchy, and next to the Royal Family, the greateſt ſufferer in the fall.</p>
            <p>But fourthly, if we take this Principle, that has raiſed ſuch great clamours againſt the Divine right of the Church, and view it in thoſe concluſions, which unavoidably flow from it, we ſhall find it the moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumelious and deſtructive to Government, of any thing that has appeared againſt it. And though I do not charge the concluſions upon all, who have owned the Principle; yet we may be allowed to take them from one, who well enough underſtands, and is not aſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to ſpeak out the juſt conſequence of his premiſes.</p>
            <p>Does not he then, who denies the Obligation of Chriſtianity, upon this ground, that there is no Law antecedent to the Civil Sanction, at the ſame time take the Law of Nature out of Mens heart, and a God out of the World, who is the Author, and Avenger of it? And does he not thereby put a People that ſhould profeſs it, out of the protection of the Law of Nations? For what Faith can be expected from him, who does not yet own it to be his Duty? And how can he acknowledge it to be his Duty, who denies a God to revenge and puniſh the, violation of it? Does not he, who makes the arbitrary pleaſure of the Magiſtrate the ſole Rule and Standard of Good and Evil, take away from the Prince, the deſerved commendations of Juſtice, and Wiſdom, and all thoſe other Virtues, which are the moſt ſparkling Diamonds in his Crown,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:63348:21"/>making no difference at all between <hi>Tiberius</hi> and <hi>Antoninus, Nero</hi> and <hi>Titus;</hi> the peſt, and the darling of Mankind? Is the Prince any thing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding to him for this pretended extent of the bounds of the Civil Power, who at the ſame time places that power in poſſeſſion, and ſtrength, and the ſame right in an uſurping Tyrant, and the undoubted Soveraign? Does not he, who holds it his duty, to forſwear Chriſtianity at the command of the Magiſtrate, declare himſelf perfidious to the Government, as well as an Apoſtate from the Faith? For what truſt can be repoſed in him, in Civil Matters, who can renounce that ſolemn Covenant into which he was Baptized, and openly profeſſes, his Oath is not to be believed, when his Religion is called in queſtion? Or what tye can the Magiſtrate have upon him, who can make ſo bold with his God.</p>
            <p>So fatal and pernicious is this exorbitant right of the <hi>Leviathan</hi>'s Common-wealth: It is a two edged Sword, which he puts into the Magiſtrates hands, the one merely pretending to protect the People, the other really deſigned to deſtroy the Prince. Such are the abſurd Paradoxes, which the denyal of Church-power reſolves it ſelf into. All which, with a great many others, are ſo groſs and prodigious, that if ever the Church hath ſhow'd her ſelf undutiful to the State, it is in ſuffering ſuch a peſtilent Enemy to Government to enjoy the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of her Communion.</p>
            <p>There is a ſecond pretence, againſt the intereſt
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:63348:21"/>of the Holy Ghoſt, in a Biſhops Conſecration, That Chriſt gave the fulneſs of his Spirit only to St. <hi>Peter</hi> and his Succeſſors, but nothing to the other Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, who ſeem to be joyned in Commiſſion with him. So that whatever power and authority is enjoyed by Biſhops, who ſucceed them, they hold it not immediately from Chriſt, but only as Suffra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans of his pretended Vicar. But, ſince this is a point, in which the <hi>Roman</hi> Schools are divided among themſelves, as appears, by the contrary aſſertions of <hi>Soto, Victoria, Alphonſus à Caſtro,</hi> and others; and the Diſpute ſeems at laſt to be reſolved, rather into the exerciſe of the Power; or, as the Schools love to ſpeak, the application of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of it, than the power it ſelf; it is properly the ſubject of another conſideration, and does not ſo directly contradict, what we have hitherto con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded from the Text. And therefore, I ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to raiſe an inference, or two, from the Holy Ghoſts Concerment in the collation of Epiſcopal Power, which will likewiſe take in the remaining part of my Diviſion.</p>
            <p>Firſt then, if <hi>the Holy Ghoſt has made you Biſhops,</hi> you may hence infer the weight and burden of your Calling. It is ſure no ordinary employment, where the Commiſſion for it comes under the Broad Seal of Heaven. 'Twas God that gave the Law upon Mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> and therefore <hi>Moſes,</hi> who was to deliver it to the People, <hi>exceedingly quakes and trembles.</hi> And, if St. <hi>Paul</hi> be rapt up into the third Heaven, to receive Inſtructions for the Goſpel,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:63348:22"/>we preſently hear of his Reproaches, and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſes, and the great trouble coming upon him, from <hi>the care of all the Churches.</hi> No wonder there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, if, when he had acquainted the perſons here in the Text, with the derivation of their Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, he forthwith preſents them with a proſpect of their danger. His own encounter at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> could not procure that reſt, and quiet for the Biſhops, he left behind him, but that after his departure, there were beaſts to be fought with ſtill. <hi>For this I know, that grievous Wolves ſhall enter in among you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall not here take upon me the work of an Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorian, nor give an account, how in all Ages of the Church, the luſts of the Fleſh, and the Devils of Hell, have, with their utmoſt Malice, ſet them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves againſt it. If we do but open our Eyes, and behold the preſent face of Religion among our ſelves, we ſhall find arguments enough to call forth your ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt circumſpection. <hi>A great door is open to you , and many adverſaries.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For if that turbulent Spirit of Rebellion and Diſobedience, which, not long ſince poſſeſt, rent, and tore this Nation, and was, by a Miracle of his Providence, a while ſince caſt out, walks about night and day, ſeeking to return to the place from whence he came, with ſeven other Spirits, more wicked than himſelf, ſo to make our laſt eſtate prove worſe than the former: If there are ſo many <hi>Tobiahs,</hi> and <hi>Sanballats,</hi> that envy the remainders of the proſperity of <hi>Sion,</hi> ſo many <hi>Zebahs,</hi> and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:63348:22"/>
               <hi>Zalmunahs,</hi> that ſay to one another, <hi>Let us take unto our ſelves the houſes of God in poſſeſſion,</hi> that ſeek to alienate, or diminiſh the Churches Rights, robbing God <hi>in Tithes and Offerings,</hi> and then ſay, Wherein have we robb'd him? If the fiery <hi>Jeſuit</hi> on the one hand, and the reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs <hi>Fanatick</hi> on the other, bend all their wit and power, firſt <hi>to ſmite the Shepherd,</hi> and then to ſcatter and glean up the Sheep; compaſſing Sea and Land to make Proſelytes, and when they have gained them, making them ten times more the Children of Hell, than themſelves: If what St. <hi>Paul,</hi> Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſied at <hi>Epheſus</hi> be now fulfilled with us, that <hi>of our ſelves men ariſe, ſpeaking perverſe things, to draw away Diſciples after them,</hi> and ſtretching the Articles of the Church of <hi>England</hi> to ſo much a greater latitude, than the <hi>Catholick</hi> Church allows, that for as much, as in them lies, <hi>Pelagius</hi> and <hi>Socinus,</hi> ſhall find here both ſhelter, and encouragement. Laſtly, if there be ſo many Hereticks in the World, that corrupt the Church of Chriſt, Schiſmaticks that divide it, and Atheiſts, that contemn it; It is then ſurely high time for you to look about you, to <hi>contend earneſtly for the Faith which was once delivered to the Saints;</hi> to joyn your Heads, your Hearts, and your Hands together, to ſupport the tottering Ark, which is now no longer Criminal, and keep it from ever returning into the Tents of the <hi>Philiſtins,</hi> which we have ſeen ſo miraculouſly redeemed from them.</p>
            <p>But ſecondly, notwithſtanding all theſe diſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:63348:23"/>if the Holy Ghoſt have called you to your Office, you may reſt aſſured, that he will own, and protect you in the diſcharge. If you held your Callings from the World, the frowns of the World might diſcourage you: But ſince 'tis God that ſets his Seal to your Commiſſion, you ſerve a Maſter; who, let the World be never ſo impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient, will aſſuredly make good your Patent, aſſert and juſtifie your Authority. When God ſays con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Cyrus, I have called him,</hi> Iſa. 48.15. it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows in the Text, <hi>and I will make his way proſperous.</hi> If God ſay to <hi>Jacob, I have called thee,</hi> no wonder to hear the encouragement he forth with gives him, <hi>When thou goeſt through the water, I am with thee; and through the Rivers, they ſhall not overflow thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It ſeems to be an opinion among the Ancient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, that every Biſhop hath two Guardian Angels. For beſides that, which is common to him with every man, he has another, as he is a Biſhop, appointed him at his Conſecration.</p>
            <p>But the ſtability of your Function (Holy Fathers) has a ſurer ground than in theſe fancies of men. Even the God of Angels vouchſafes to become your pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar Guardian. And if the Church, like <hi>Jacob</hi>'s Ladder, though the foot of it be on Earth, has its head in Heaven, there are not only Angels aſcending and deſcending, but God himſelf leans upon the top of it, and keeps it firm.</p>
            <p>A conſideration this of great weight and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, eſpecially under the apprehenſions of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick danger: It being uſual with men, in ſuch exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:63348:23"/>as thoſe, to betake themſelves to their own Counſels and Contrivances; and when theſe fail, to deſpond, and give over; nay, ſometimes with a more prepoſterous piece of Policy, to make Ship-wrack of a good Conſcience, in hopes to eſcape the ſtorm. But ſurely, if we own ſuch a thing as Divine Protection, which is never forfeited, but by diſtruſt, we ſhall ever find it, try it when we will, that the beſt way to ſecure our ſelves from danger, is to be doing our duty. For this infallibly engages God of our ſide, who <hi>will be with us, as long as we are with him.</hi> It is ſafer for the Mariner in a Tempeſt to ride out the Storm, then to ſtrike to Shore. And we need not fear Drowning, as long as Chriſt is in the Ship.</p>
            <p>And therefore, let the <hi>Heathen</hi> rage, and the Nations take Counſel together; <hi>he that ſitteth in the Heavens, ſhall laugh them to ſcorn, the Lord ſhall have them in deriſion;</hi> he can ſhatter their Councils, blaſt their Deſigns, defeat their Purpoſes, and ruin their Confederacies: And will never fail, openly to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate, that his Church is founded upon a Rock, too firm to be ſhaken by the combinations of men; even upon the promiſe of God, and the Graces of his Spirit, things eternally invincible by the gates of Hell.</p>
            <p>Nor has God <hi>ever left himſelf without witneſs</hi> of this peculiar preſence in the greateſt diſtreſſes of his Church. Even at the firſt founding of it, when in all humane probability, it was ſo little en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled to ſtand out againſt the machinations of the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:63348:24"/>World; yet, then did the Almighty <hi>reveal his arm,</hi> and exert his Power, and in ſpite of all the oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions both of Earth and Hell, made his own Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel to ſtand, and flouriſh. 'Twas he of old, that upheld an <hi>Athanaſius contra mundum,</hi> and effectually reſcued his Church from that deluge of <hi>Arrianiſm,</hi> which to all appearance, had ſwallowed it up, and overwhelmed it.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, to name no more, but this Church of ours, under thoſe ſignal inſtances of his afflicting providence, the ſinking our gates, deſtroying our palaces, and ſlighting the ſtrong holds of <hi>Sion,</hi> when that dreadful ſtorm had utterly ſunk both the Government of our Church, and our hopes of its recovery; yet even then did the Spirit of God <hi>move upon the face of the waters,</hi> 'till at length <hi>the dry land appeared,</hi> and again reduced it to that beautiful order, which has made it ever ſince the object of Malice, and the mark of Envy.</p>
            <p>Surely therefore, he who had a favour for <hi>Sion,</hi> when her Stones were in the duſt, has not left off his concern for it, now it ſtands upon its pillars. But rather on the contrary, if the preſent methods o his Providence can give us any rule for a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecture, he ſeems to have ſome further work in hand, for the eſtabliſhment of his Church, while he ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gles out perſons of ſuch worth and eminence, for the undertaking.</p>
            <p>But thirdly, if <hi>the Holy Ghoſt hath made you Biſhops,</hi> you are entruſted by one, who will aſſuredly take an account of the Adminiſtration. It appears in
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:63348:24"/>the Records of the ancient Church, that they never brought a Biſhop to publick penance. Of which practice, this ſeems to be one reaſon among others, that, ſince there was no ſpiritual power on Earth above him, they reſerved him to the future Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the tribunal of a Lord, who alone was higher than he. And therefore, though a Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious <hi>Conſtantine</hi> thinks fit to cover the faults of his Biſhops with his own Purple, and the whole <hi>Chriſtian</hi> World at this day were as forward to hide, as they are on the contrary, to reveal their Fathers nakedneſs; Yet all theſe coverings ſignifie no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to him, who looks through them all, to him who <hi>pondereth the heart,</hi> and <hi>weigheth the ſpirits of men.</hi> All things are naked and open be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, with whom you have to do, and will one day appear ſo before the World, Angels, and Men. <hi>Take heed therefore unto your ſelves and to the flock,</hi> as thoſe that <hi>muſt give an account.</hi> And do thou (O Lord) give that ſucceſs to their Labours, that they may give it <hi>with joy and not with grief.</hi> Let thy <hi>Urim</hi> and <hi>Thummim</hi> be ſtill with <hi>thy holy ones,</hi> that their Doctrine may be no other, than that whereto thy Holy Spirit hath ſet his Seal, and their Lives and Examples may be as Sacred, as their Callings. Put Courage into their Hearts, and a Terrour upon their Faces, <hi>that with all boldneſs they may ſpeak thy word,</hi> and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain a conſtant reſolution to withſtand the Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions of the Times, that ſo in the laſt day, when the great Shepherd of the Sheep ſhall appear,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:63348:25"/>to make his final Viſitation, they may receive the Bleſſing, which belongs to thoſe, <hi>whom the Lord when he cometh ſhall find ſo doing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Well done good and faithful ſervant, thou haſt been faithful in a little, enter now into the joy of thy Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>Now to God the Father, God the Son, and God the Holy Ghoſt, three Perſons and one God, be aſcribed, as is moſt due, by us, and by all the World, all Power, Glory, Might, Majeſty, and Dominion, both now, and for evermore, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>
               <hi>P.</hi> 13. l. 20. ſuppoſitious <hi>r.</hi> ſuppoſititious.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
